"The Side Effects of Ozempic (Semaglutide)
vs. the Risks of Obesity"
Even the drug manufacturers
of Ozempic
and similar weight-loss drugs
cop to the long list
of potentially serious
side effects.
The absolute risks, though,
for serious issues
like pancreatitis,
thyroid cancer,
bowel obstruction,
were all about 1% or less
per year
of using GLP-1-type drugs.
Of course, when millions
of people are on these drugs,
even relatively rare
side effects
will occur
in a large number of people.
But you know what else
can have serious side effects?
Obesity.
In fact, one potential
side effect of GLP-1 drugs
is that they could be
too effective,
risking excessive weight loss,
suppressing the appetite
so much, for example,
that after taking
her first dose,
this patient decided
to start a new diet
composed of water and diet soda.
Or an "eat once a week" plan.
Any discussion
of risks versus benefits
has to take any benefits
of the weight loss itself
into account.
Excess body fat
is a major risk factor
for metabolic diseases,
involving nearly
every organ in our body,
such as Type II diabetes,
heart disease, stroke,
dementia, liver disease,
sleep apnea,
osteoarthritis, infertility,
several cancers,
including breast cancer
and colon cancer,
even psychiatric disorders.
Consider
the overall health outcomes
of those undergoing
bariatric surgery,
which is not exactly
a benign procedure.
In the United States,
for instance,
hundreds of thousands
go under the knife
to lose weight.
Roux-en-Y gastric bypass
is one of
the most popular techniques
and is thought to be
the "gold standard" method
given its safety record,
with a mortality rate
less 0.5%.
Wait, they’re bragging
about not killing
more than 1 in 200 people
in the operating room?
The surgery
is a major rearrangement
of your digestive tract,
but it can induce
a long-term weight loss
of about 25%,
which is similar
to some of the best results
of the new GLP-1 drugs.
So, if you only care
about living longer,
might the benefits
of weight loss
outweigh the risks of dying
on the operating table?
Based on a meta-analysis
of millions of patients,
only about 1 in 1,250 people
appear to be killed
directly by the surgery,
and since the ones
who don’t lose their lives
tend to lose so much weight,
bariatric surgery
has been associated
with a six-year longer lifespan.
So, on average,
choosing to go under the knife
may significantly
extend your life,
even after taking into account
the risk
of the operation itself
killing you.
But, of course, there’s also
the risk of complications.
Approximately 1 in 4
bariatric surgery patients
experience adverse effects
in the five years
following surgery,
and for 1 in 50,
it’s so bad
that they have to go back
onto the operating table
for further surgery.
That’s one advantage
of the drug approach.
If you experience
some serious side effect,
it may go away
when you stop taking the drug,
whereas if you’ve already
had your stomach cut out,
or your intestines rearranged,
there may be less
that can be done about it.
Here’s a list
of the pros and cons.
Researchers looked at
the impact of bariatric surgery
on more than five dozen
health outcomes.
And although people
who underwent surgery
may be more likely
to kill themselves,
break bones,
and suffer acid reflux,
they also appear
to get less diabetes,
high blood pressure,
and high cholesterol,
and less cancer
and cardiovascular disease.
Here’s how it breaks down.
Just looking at
the statistically
significant associations,
we can see that those
who’ve had bariatric surgery
had a lower risk of dying
from all causes put together,
as well as dying
specifically from diabetes,
cancer,
and cardiovascular disease,
but they are
at an increased risk
of taking their own lives.
In terms of metabolic outcomes,
lower risks of getting diabetes,
high blood pressure
and high cholesterol.
Lower risks of continuing
to have diabetes,
high blood pressure,
and cholesterol,
and a lower risk
of diabetic complications.
In terms of getting cancer,
there’s a lower risk
of developing
different types of cancer
and getting
any kind of cancer at all.
A lower risk of all
the cardiovascular diseases
the researchers looked at,
and most
of the digestive diseases
except for reflux
with sleeve gastrectomy,
and higher or lower risk
of kidney stones
depending on procedure,
but it generally seems
to be kidney protective.
For women’s health,
after bariatric surgery,
they had less
urinary incontinence
and polycystic ovary syndrome,
and fewer problems
during pregnancy,
though the outcomes
for infants are mixed,
with more preterm
birth and death.
And finally,
less anxiety and depression,
though more self-harm,
and a lower risk
of being hospitalized
and dying from COVID.
So, generally, the benefits
far outweigh the risks,
but, really, that says less
about the benefits of surgery
and more about the risks
of excess body fat.
With the GLP-1 drugs,
we see
largely similar improvements
in things like
blood sugar control,
blood pressure,
and cholesterol,
and maybe even
similar clinical outcomes,
like the risk of dying.
If that were the case,
then for most people
with obesity,
like with the bariatric surgery,
the benefits of these new drugs
would be expected
to far exceed the risks.
Yes, there are still issues
with the cost
of these potentially
life-long medications,
and lack of knowledge
of their long-term side effects,
and this, of course,
assumes you’re taking
the actual drug.
Shortages of these pills
have led patients
to compounding pharmacies
that offer versions of the drugs
that have not been approved
by the U.S. Food
and Drug Administration,
which in the past has led
to serious safety issues,
like an epidemic
of fungal meningitis
caused by moldy bottles of drugs
from compounding pharmacies.
751 patients
were ultimately affected,
and more than 60 patients died.
But at least
compounding pharmacies
have some kind of regulation.
Nowadays,
people can get injected
with God knows what
at so-called medical spas
that may not be under
any form of regulation.
People don’t seem
to be paying much attention
to these FDA warnings.
As an article
in Rolling Stone put it,
"The FDA warned Ozempic users,"
but, "They don’t give a ..."
Yes, these drugs
can improve risk factors,
but the risk-benefit analysis
really depends on
these clinical disease outcomes.
Do people really live longer
on these drugs?
Have less heart attacks?
That’s exactly
what I’ll cover, next.